Guide to the George Jacob Abbot Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Jacob Abbot papers
1811-1901
MS 28
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes, 1 folio)
Minister and diplomat. Correspondence largely relating to Abbot's service as secretary to Daniel Webster and as an agent of the State Department in England and Canada. Included are 104 letters by Daniel Webster as well as copies of several of his speeches. State Department papers concerning controversies with England (1837-1852), newspaper clippings about Daniel Webster and miscellaneous receipts, inventories and photographs make up the remainder of the papers.
Abbot, George Jacob, 1812-1879
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wilkie Bushby in 1955.
Arrangement
Arranged in five sections: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, Printed Matter, and Newspaper Clippings.
Scope and Contents
The George Jacob Abbot Papers consist mainly of correspondence, drafts of speeches, unfinished drafts of U.S. State Department papers, newspaper clippings and other materials related to Abbot's employment as secretary to Daniel Webster and to his diplomatic service. There are some Abbot family materials among the papers as well.
The correspondence consists of approximately 700 letters, of which 104 (1811-1852) are by Webster and 74 are to him, and 247 (1842-1878) are by Abbot and 175 to him. Nearly half of Abbot's letters were written during his diplomatic service in England and Canada. Among the important correspondents are Thomas Stephenson, U.S. Consular Agent; Emory McClintock, Vice-consul at Sheffield; Prentiss Mellen, first Chief Justice of Maine; and judges Charles Jackson, James Kent, and Joseph Story. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, but the letters are individually catalogued in the Department's manuscript catalogue, and a list of correspondents follow the folder listing.
The speeches include copies of Webster's Fourth of July speech of 1851 and a speech delivered before the New York Historical Society in 1852. There are several copies of other speeches as well as notes and fragments pertaining to them. These are untitled and undated.
The State Department drafts relate to the British attack on the American steamer Caroline in 1837, to the fisheries dispute with England in 1851, and to the case of John S. Thrasher, and American being held in Cuba, 1851-1852.
The newspaper clippings are mainly reviews of Webster's speeches and reports of his political activities.
Other materials, presumably related to Abbot's secretarial duties, include receipts, inventories, lists of names and photographs. A folio contains a certificate of appointment, signed by Millard Fillmore and Daniel Webster, of George King Rogers to the U.S. Consulate in France and a chart of the square mileage of each state and territory of the United States.
Not directly related to Abbot's employment is a draft deposition (ca. 1776) by Peter Green concerning loyalist activities in the colonies.
Abbot's family is represented by a manuscript sermon of his father, Rev. Jacob Abbot (1768-1834); "A Record of the Last Days of Daniel Webster," an unpublished manuscript by Mary J. C. Throop, Abbot's daughter (b. 1842); and by school examination papers of Anna Abbot Throop, Abbot's grandaughter (b. 1869). A printed sermon,Discourse Delivered in Windham, N.H., November 5, 1834, at the Internment of Rev. Jacob Abbot… (Nashua, N.H.: Alfred Beard, 1835), has been transferred to the Yale Divinity Library
The Daniel Webster materials were presumably gathered by Abbot for use in preparing the six volumes of the Works of Daniel Webster(Boston, 1851). Most of Edward Everett's letters to Abbot refer to the editing and production of the Works. Apparently the Webster papers were also used by Mrs. Throop in preparing her manuscript.
The George Jacob Abbot Papers were given to Yale University Library by Wilkie Bushby in September 1955.
Biographical / Historical
George Jacob Abbot, son of the Rev. Jacob Abbot, a Unitarian minister, was born in Windham, N.H. He graduated from Harvard College in 1835, after which he opened a boys' school in Washington, D.C. After a clerkship in the State Department, he became private secretary to Daniel Webster, this during Webster's second term as Secretary of State (1850-1852).
Abbot served as United States consul at Bradford and Sheffield, England, from 1864 to 1870 and, returning to the U.S., was for several years a professor at the Theological School at Meadville, P.A. In 1877 he took another diplomatic position at Goderich and Windsor, Canada, which he maintained until his death.
More information as to Abbot and family may be found in Leonard A. Morrison's History of Windham in New Hampshire, 1719-1883 (Boston: Cupples, Upham and Co., 1883).
Appendix
List of Correspondents
Abbot, Ann T.G. (Emery) [2], 1851
Abbot George Jacob (including 10 to his wife, 4 to Edward Everitt, 102 to Emory McClintock, 3 to Mary J.C. (Abbot) Throop, 108 to U.S. Dept. of State, 4 to Daniel Webster) [247], 1842-1878
Adams, Charles Francis [1], 1893-1895, 1899, 1905
Allen, J.H. [3], 1851
Ames, C. [1], 1852
Andrews, J. DeWolf [9], 1851-1852
Appleton, William [3], 1861, n.d.
Archer, William Segar [1], 1852
Barnard, Daniel Dewey [1], 1852
Barnard, James S. [1], 1852
Barnett, John [1], 1852
Barney, John (5 tel., 1) [6], 1852
Bates, Issac C. [1], 1851
Bible Society of Washington [1], 1852
Bayly, B.S. [3], 1852
Bird, Josiah N. [1], 1852
Brooks, E. [1], 1851
Brosseau, A & Co. [1], 1865
Brown, John P. [1], 1851
Brunner, William & Co. [1], 1865
Buel, C.C. [1], 1900
Burritt, Elihu [1], 1870
Burwell, William M. [2], 1851
Cable, Joseph, 1852
Carazza, Lizzie [1], n.d.
Chandler, Joseph Ripley [1], 1850
Choate, Rufus [1], n.d.
Conrad, Charles M. [2], 1852
Cooper, James [1], 1851
Crampton, Sir John Fiens Twisleton [1], 1852,
Cupid, Josephine [1], 1851
Curtis, Edward [2], 1852
Curtis, George Ticknor [3], 1852-1859
Cushing, Caleb [1], 1858
Cutts, J. Madison [2], 1851-1852
Darby, William [1], 1851
Davis, George Thomas [2], 1852, n.d.
Dayton, William L. [2], n.d.
Dexter, Franklin [1], 1850
Dix, Dorothea Lynde [1], 1887,
Dorr, E. Richie [1], 1851
Dutton, Warren [1], 1830
Dudley, Thomas H. [1], 1868
Easby, William [1], 1851
Eckert, G.N. (as director of U.S. Mint) [1], 1851
Edgerton, Alfred Peck [1], 1852
Eliot, William G. [1], 1851
Ethridge, John [1], 1851
Evans, Henry G. [1], 1851,
Everett, Alexander Hill [1], 1851
Everett, Edward [20], 1851-1859
Farnham, R. [1], 1851
Felton, Cornelius Conway [3], 1852-1860
Fillmore, Millard (to Daniel Webster) [2], 1852
Foreman, E. [1], 1852
Fosdick, David [2], 1851
"Friends of Daniel Webster" [7], 1850-1851
Fuller, Hiram [6], 1814-1880
Fulton, Charles C. [1], 1851
Gaitley, Kate [1], 1886
Gales, Joseph [1], 1851
Gaston, William [1], 1820
Gilman, Arthur [1], 1889
Gooch, William B. [1], 1851
Goodrich, Samuel Griswold [1], [1852?],
Goodrich, Charles J. [1], 1852
Goodrich, Zacheus [1], 1852
Gay (or Guy), William [1], 185-?
George Washington University [1], 1851
Hale, Nathan [1], 1851
Harrington, George [2], 1851
Haskins, Nat [1], 1851
Hawley, E. [1], 1850
Hayes, Caroline L. [1], 1851
Heyer, W. Grant [1], 1852
Hunter, Louisa [1], n.d.
Hunter, William [2], 1852
Jackson, Charles [4], 1830-1839
Jewett, Charles Coffin [4], 1851
Johnson, R. [1], 1851? (or 1861?)
Kebler, John [2], 1851
Kebler, Lucy (Abbot) [1], 1851
Kelly, Samuel [1], 1851
Kenney, B.G. [4], 1851
Kent, James [1], 1830
Ketchum, Hiram [5], 1852
Kiderlin, William L.J. [1], 1852
Kimball, Richard Burleigh [1], 1852
King, Horatio [3], 1865
Kingmen, E. [1], 1852
Lander, Edward [1], 1853
Lanman, Charles [3], 1852
Laurence, A.H. [1], 1852
Lawson, C. [1], 1852
Lawson, Thomas [1], 1852
Letcher, Robert P. [1], 1851
Lester, Charles Edwards [1], 1852
Levin, Lewis C. [1], 1852
Little, Brown & Co. [1], 1852
Lord, Henry W. [2], 1865
McKean, W.V. [1], 1853
Mackie, James S. [1], 1851
Marcy, William Learned [1], n.d.
Manchester, N.Y. (Citizens of) [1], 1851
Marston, John M. [3], 1851
Mechanics' Institute, Bradford, England [1], 1865
Mitchell, Mr. & Mrs. Henry [1], 1899
Moore, George Henry [2], 1852, n.d.
Moore, Helen [1], 1850
Morgan, Lewis Henry [1], 1851
Morris, Charles [1], 1852
Morrison, Ann Theresa (Abbot) [2], 1852-1857
Morse, John M. [1], 1851
Mountfort, George [1], 1851
Mundella, Anthony John [1], 1870
Munroe, J. & Co. [1], 1851
Murray, Patrick [1], 1852
Nichols, Julia Webster (Abbot) [3], 1871-1891
Norton, Charles B. [1], 1851
Nourse, Joseph Everett [1], 1851
Noyes, Parker [1], 1852
Osgood, George [2], 1851
Peck, Cassius P. [1], 1852
Porter, E. [1], 1852
Porter, John K. [1], 1851
Powell, C.H. [1], 1851
Randall, H.K. [2], 1852
Rankin, M.M. [4], 1865
Rawson, Francis George [1], 1865
Rodice, M.E. [1], 1851
Sanborn, C.P. [1], 1851
Seward, William Henry [1], n.d.
Shattuck, W.G. [1], 1851
Skinner, Aaron Nichols [1], 1852
Smith, Samuel Abbot [1], 1851
Smith, W. Ramsden [1], 1865
Smith W. & Sons [1], 1865
Stephenson, Thomas [34], 1856-1865
Stevenson, R.M. [3], 1865
Story, Joseph [8], 1824-1840
Taylor, Frank [2], 1851
Taylor, H. [1], 1852
Thomas, Charles [1], 1851
Thrasher, John Sidney [1], 1853
Throop, Mary J.C. (Abbot) [4], 1851-1883
Totten, Joseph Gilbert [1], 1851
Ticknor, George [2], 1852
Trenton, N.J., Lawyers and Legislators [1], 1852
Train, George Francis [1], 1853
Unidentified [11], 1851-1892
U.S. Census Office [3], 1851
U.S. Department of the Interior [1] (folio), 1851
U.S. Department of State [18], 1850-1857
U.S. Department of State (Comm. to G.K. Rogers as Consul at Lyons) [1], 1852
U.S. Treasury Department [2], 1851-1865
U.S. War Department [1], 1851
U.S. Navy Department [1], 1851
Varnum, Joseph Bradley Jr. [1], 1851
Vick, Bushrod W. [2], 1852
Walsh, Charles T.?. [1], 1851
Warren, G.W. [1], 1852
Webb, John F. [1], 1851
Webb, William Benning [1], 1851
Webster, Daniel (drafts & some originals including 15 to G.J. Abbot, 1851-1852, and 11 to Millard Fillmore, 1852) [104], 1811-1852
Wehrmann, L.F. [1], 1851? (or 1852?)
Wells, Israel, et.al. [1], 1852
Wieting, Christopher [1], 1852
William, J. Howard [1], 1852
Winthrop, Robert Charles [2], 1850-1859
Wood, George [1], 1851
Fisheries -- United States; Canada -- Foreign relations -- United States; Canada; Cuba -- Foreign relations -- United States; Europe; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- United States; New England; United States -- Foreign relations -- Canada; United States -- Foreign relations -- Cuba; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government; Photoprints; Clergy; Diplomats; Abbot, George Jacob, 1812-1879; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Fuller, Hiram, 1814-1880; Jackson, Charles, 1775-1855; Jewett, Charles C. (Charles Coffin), 1816-1868; Kent, James, 1763-1847; King, Horatio, 1811-1897; Mellen, Prentiss, 1764-1840; Stephenson, Thomas; Story, Joseph, 1779-1845; Thrasher, J. S. (John Sidney), 1817-1879; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; United States. Department of State
- Inventory, [1776?], 1811-1901; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Correspondence
    - 1811-1865 May (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
    - 1865 June-1900, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-26)
  - Drafts of Daniel Webster's Fourth of July speech, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Drafts of Daniel Webster's Fourth of July speech, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Drafts of Daniel Webster's Fourth of July speech, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Drafts of Daniel Webster's address to the New York Historical Society, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Speeches by Daniel Webster, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Notes and drafts re: the Works of Daniel Webster, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "A Record of the Last Days of Daniel Webster" by Mary J. C. Throop, [1899?] (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Drafts of U.S. Department of State papers re: the Caroline affair, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Drafts of U.S. Department of State papers re: the John S. Thrasher case, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Drafts of U.S. Department of State papers re: the fisheries dispute with England, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Notes, fragments of speeches and other materials by Webster and others, [1850s?] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Memoranda re: government, law and other matters, [1850s?] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Lists, receipts and inventories re: Webster and Abbot, [1850s?] (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - List of names and addresses, calling cards, and envelopes, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Photographs of Webster's birthplace and unidentified landscape, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets by Daniel Webster and others, 1834-1884 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter re: Daniel Webster, 1850-1852 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "Sermon of my Grandfather, Rev. Jacob Abbot", undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - School examination papers and printed matter of Anna A. Throop and Mary J. C. Throop, 1883-1900 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Peter Green's deposition re: loyalty to Great Britain, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1851, 1850s, 1884, 1898, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 47-51)
  - Annotated clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Certificate of appointment, signed by Millard Fillmore and Daniel Webster, of George King Rogers to the U.S. Consulate in France, 1852 February 9 (Box 5)
  - Chart of the square mileage of each state and territory of the United States in 1793 and 1851, 1851 June 25 (Box 5)